<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>vectors on francojc ⟲</title>
    <link>https://francojc.github.io/tags/vectors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in vectors on francojc ⟲</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2018 by Jerid Francom</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://francojc.github.io/tags/vectors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Acquiring data for language research (3/3): web scraping </title>
      <link>https://francojc.github.io/2017/11/02/acquiring-data-for-language-research-web-scraping/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://francojc.github.io/2017/11/02/acquiring-data-for-language-research-web-scraping/</guid>
      <description>Web scraping There are many resources available through direct downloads from repositories and individual sites and R package interfaces to web resources with APIs, but these resources are relatively limited to the amount of public-facing textual data recorded on the web. In the case that you want to acquire data from webpages R can be used to access the web programmatically through a process known as web scraping. The complexity of web scrapes can vary but in general it requires more advanced knowledge of R as well as the structure of the language of the web: HTML (Hypertext Markup Language).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acquiring data for language research (2/3): package interfaces</title>
      <link>https://francojc.github.io/2017/10/23/acquiring-data-for-language-research-package-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://francojc.github.io/2017/10/23/acquiring-data-for-language-research-package-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>Package interfaces A convenient alternative method for acquiring data in R is through package interfaces to web services. These interfaces are built using R code to make connections with resources on the web through Automatic Programming Interfaces (APIs). Websites such as Project Gutenberg, Twitter, Facebook, and many others provide APIs to allow access to their data under certain conditions, some more limiting for data collection than others. Programmers (like you!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>