<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>census on francojc ⟲</title>
    <link>https://francojc.github.io/tags/census/</link>
    <description>Recent content in census on francojc ⟲</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jerid Francom</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://francojc.github.io/tags/census/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping US Census data and adding Twitter posts</title>
      <link>https://francojc.github.io/2016/03/08/mapping-us-census-data-and-adding-twitter-posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://francojc.github.io/2016/03/08/mapping-us-census-data-and-adding-twitter-posts/</guid>
      <description>Not all tweets have geolocation information available. Accessing the Twitter API via the streamR package particular parameters can be set to only include those tweets with geolocation enabled. You can also specify a bounding box to further filter the geographic area from which you would like to draw your sample tweets. Now, the bounding box is going to be just that, a box. And we are dealing with polygons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping US Census data</title>
      <link>https://francojc.github.io/2016/02/06/mapping-us-census-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://francojc.github.io/2016/02/06/mapping-us-census-data/</guid>
      <description>I’m currently working on a project involving Twitter posts and demographics. One of the best resources for demographic information in the US is the census. Having not worked with US census data in a very long time, I was excited to see that there is an R package available to make the process easier.
In this exploRation I will provide a tutorial on 1) how to acquire the US census data and other demographic data through American Fact Finder, 2) how to visualize the data in regional choropleths, 3) how to overlay geo-tagged tweets, and finally 4) how to display the map as an interactive plot.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>