<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recipe on francojc ⟲</title>
    <link>/categories/recipe/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recipe on francojc ⟲</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Jerid Francom</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/recipe/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic word frequency analysis</title>
      <link>/2017/07/30/basic-word-frequency-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/30/basic-word-frequency-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this Recipe you will learn the steps to import text data into R from your computer, create a word frequency list, and generate a plot based on these word frequencies. Calculating word frequency, and frequency of occurrence of any other linguistic unit, is a core aspect of any data analysis project. Along the way I will also introduce some key programming concepts, in particular variable assignment, ‘piping’ (using the &lt;code&gt;magrittr&lt;/code&gt; package), and custom functions. The aim here, then, is to help you build your confidence working with text in R and become generally more familiar with the first steps in any corpus analysis workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;import-a-text-file&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Import a text file&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R is equipped to read data from various sources. The most basic source is the ‘plain text’ file, often suffixed with the &lt;code&gt;.txt&lt;/code&gt; extension. Plain text files are just that; files which have no formatting at all. They only contain characters encoded in electronic form.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; To read text into R from your computer you need to know two things: 1) where the file (or files) reside, that is what the path is from your working directory to the file(s) and 2) how the file is structured internally. The path is easy. First you need to find out where your current R session is currently working from with the following command:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Find our current working directory
getwd()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the moment we will assume Unicode encoding, but in practice there are still lingering files floating around on the web that will be encoded in some other format including ASCII, Latin-1, &lt;em&gt;etc.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice that I’ve added a &lt;em&gt;comment&lt;/em&gt; before the &lt;code&gt;getwd()&lt;/code&gt; command. These comments are for humans, not R. You are highly encouraged comment your code as it makes it clear what the purpose of the code is.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with R and RStudio</title>
      <link>/2017/07/30/getting-started-with-r-and-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/30/getting-started-with-r-and-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Downloading and installing R …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with R in the default GUI and the command-line …&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing the Recipe series</title>
      <link>/2017/07/30/introducing-the-recipe-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/30/introducing-the-recipe-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About this series…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About R …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why R …&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
